An Annotated Calendar of the Letters of Charles Darwin in the Library of the American Philosophical Society 1799-1882 Mss.B.D25
American Philosophical Society
The following individuals aided in transcribing, dating, locating, and/or annotating one or more letters: Marianne Abel, Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia; John Angell, Free Library of Philadelphia; Sir Hedley Atkins, M.D., Down House; Suzanne W. Brown, Chicago Academy of Sciences; Colin Burton, Baird & Tatlock (London) Ltd.; Dr. Ralph Colp, Jr.; Professor Joseph Ewan, Department of Biology, Tulane University; Ellen G. Gartrell, Assistant Curator, Historical Collections, College of Physicians of Philadelphia; Sheila K. Hart, Harvard College Library; F. A. Milligan, Hereford and Worcester County [England] Libraries; Professor James A. Rogers, Department of History, Claremont Men's College; Jeffrey L. Sturchio, Department of the History and Sociology of Science, University of Pennsylvania; Margaret Teransky, Free Library of Philadelphia; Philip Titheradge, Down House; and Professor David B. Wilson, Department of History, University of Oklahoma. My colleague and friend Roy Goodman here in the Library is unparalleled as a reference librarian.
In the course of my research, I have enjoyed the facilities of and/or received the competent assistance of the staffs of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia, the Burndy Library, the Chicago Academy of Sciences, the Harvey S. Firestone Library of Princeton University, the Free Library of Philadelphia, the Harvard College Library, the Hereford and Worcester County [England] Libraries, the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, and the Charles Patterson Van Pelt Library of the University of Pennsylvania. I am also grateful to all those persons and institutions mentioned in the second appendix for making its compilation possible. A copy of the Darwin letter to Gray which I quote in the introduction was provided by the Gray Herbarium, Harvard University, which has the original. Those who have graciously given permission for reproduction of one or another of the illustrations are acknowledged where the figures appear.
Preparation of this calendar has consumed much of my time and attention over the last two years. Accordingly, I should like to thank the faculty, the staff, and my fellow graduate students in the Department of the History and Sociology of Science at the University of Pennsylvania for tolerating my reduced visibility around the Department. Similarly, my wife Nan, my late father, and my mother have suffered me cheerfully whenever the excesses of my enthusiasm for Darwin and the history of science have overflowed into my family life.
Many others, too numerous to mention, have aided the compilation of this volume in some way. Despite all this help, endless factual and interpretive errors, of which I am painfully aware and for which I am solely responsible, undoubtedly remain. I hope that scholars will both forgive me for these and report them to the Library for the benefit of future students of Darwin.
P. T. C.
Related materials
Although Darwin's correspondence is very widely dispersed, the largest collection of Darwin Papers is housed at the Cambridge University Library (http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/MSS/Darwin.html). Cambridge hosts an on-line calendar of Darwin correspondence at http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/Departments/Darwin/calintro.html.
The Getz Collection (B D25.m) contains additional Darwin Papers, and the Library houses the complete files of the Darwin Papers Editorial Project (Ms. Coll. 28) (including photocopies of all extant Darwin letters) and microfilm of Darwin materials held at Down House (films 496,13; 496,14), along with material relating to Erasmus Darwin and other members of the Darwin family.
In addition to manuscript letters to and from Charles Darwin, several other items in the Library of the American Philosophical Society may be of interest to the Darwin scholar. These are discussed below in more-or-less general way which, although not a comprehensive list, should give readers some idea of the nature of these collections. The items are discussed in groups, by type of document.
Manuscript items
Included under this rubric are three types of documents:
the correspondence and other papers of those people who corresponded with Darwin--all of it relating directly to manuscript letters calendared above
autograph documents from Darwin's own papers or from others, but relating directly to Darwin and not connected to any of the manuscript letters calendared above; and
manuscript correspondence to and from other members of the Darwin family besides Charles Darwin.
There are seven items of the first type. All of these pertain to the case of the inheritance of an injury in a goose, as related to Darwin by Reuben A. Blair in the correspondence with him calendared above. The documents are: 1) a photograph of the deformed goose; 2) a letter from Blair concerning the goose and printed in the Sedalia Democrat; 3) a letter from William Henry Flower to Blair; 4) the report by Flower and his assistant, Dr. Larson, on the wings of the affected geese; 5) a letter from Blair to an unnamed correspondent; and 6) letters exchanged between Blair and Spencer Fullerton Baird of the Smithsonian Institution.
There are twenty items of the second type. These documents are: 1) five leaves from the manuscript of the Origin of Species; 2) a signed page from the manuscript of the Descent of Man; 3) a signed page from some other Darwin manuscript (discusses Catasetum); 4) a printed petition for the endowment of research, issued by J. Norman Lockyer and C. E. Appleton, and signed by Darwin; 5) the final page of the petition for a pension for Alfred Russel Wallace, signed by twelve persons, including Darwin; 6) sketches of Darwin, his wife, grandson, and dog, by Albert Goodwin; 7) documents pertaining to Darwin's funeral in Westminster Abbey (eleven items); 8) inscription from the Carroll # 372 statue of Darwin at Oxford University; 9) a discussion of Darwin's B: D25.176 religion by H. Buxton Forman; and 10) a pass to the Zoological Gardens, issued to James Gough by Darwin.
There are 44 items of the third type, which is too many to list individually here. Members of the Darwin family involved in this correspondence are: Emma Wedgwood Darwin (two letters, correspondence with Mrs. Georgiana Rosetta Smyth Flower and with John Maurice Herbert); Francis Darwin (39 letters, correspondence with Leo Abram Errera, George John Romanes, Thomas Roscoe Rede Stebbing, and Otto Zacharias); and George Howard Darwin (three letters, correspondence with F. W. Surman and Otto Zacharias).
Photocopies of manuscript items
The Library has 26 documents pertaining to Darwin, the originals of which are located elsewhere; only photographically-reproduced paper copies of the documents are at the APS. These fall into two categories: photocopies of manuscript correspondence with Darwin; and photocopies of Darwin-related documents from the papers of Darwin correspondents. In the first category, there are copies of correspondence with the College of Physicians of Philadelphia (one letter), Ignatius Donnelly (two letters), Hugo de Vries (one letter), Benjamin Dann Walsh (eighteen letters), and Jeffries Wyman (two letters). In the second category, there is a photocopy of a letter from Frank J. Mead, editor of the Minneapolis Evening Times, to Ignatius Donnelly, concerning Darwinism and Christianity, and a photocopy of a portion of Donnelly's diary which mentions Darwin.
Microfilms of manuscript items
The Library has nine sets of microfilms of Darwin materials which are on deposit at various institutions all over the world. These films contain the following: 1) correspondence in possession of Down House, Kent (one reel); 2) correspondence in the Robert Stecher Collection at the Cleveland Medical Library Association (one reel); 3) correspondence in the New York Botanical Garden (one reel); letters to Auguste H. Forel, from originals in the Medicinhistorisches Institut, University of Switzerland, and in University of Basel Library (sixteen frames); 4) letters to Bernhard Studer and to A. von Morlot (seven items); 5) letters to J. Moulinie, A. Dohrn, Karl Christoph Vogt, Pictet, and de la Rive, from originals in the Bibliotheque Publique et Universitaire de Geneve (25 letters); 6) notebooks written during the voyage of the Beagle, from Down House, Kent (eighteen notebooks, one reel); 7) diary and correspondence written during the voyage of the Beagle, from Down House, Kent (one reel); and 9) chronology and bibliography of Darwin's life, compiled by Sir Gavin de Beer, containing an incomplete list of all of Darwin's correspondence (two reels).
Photographs and prints
The Library has approximately twelve different photographs and prints of Darwin and of Down House. Some of the best of these are used as illustrations in this calendar.
Books
There are about 150 copies of various editions of Darwin's works in the Library, plus a fair collection of some of the rarer and/or more significant editions of the works of his correspondents, colleagues, and contemporary naturalists and biologists. Space does not permit a full listing of the 150 works by Darwin in the Library, but it is possible to give some indication of the collection by referring to the number assigned to each edition held by the Library in the standard bibliography of Darwin's works (R. B. Freeman, The Works of Charles Darwin: An Annotated Bibliographical Handlist [London: Dawsons of Pall Mall, 1965]). The "Freeman numbers" of the Library's holdings are given below, without comment.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, 8, 10, 16, 83, 84, 85, 86, 87, 88, 89, 90, 91, 95, 99, 103, 105, 106, 108, 109, 110, 111, 112, 113, 114, 115, 116, 117, 142, 205, 207, 208, 210, 219, 220, 231, 231n, 232, 234, 246, 247, 250, 255, 269, 281, 283, 292, 297, 298, 303, 305, 308, 309, 311, 314, 315, 319, 332, 333, 334, 343, 344, 345, 346, 349, 359, 361, 362, 364, 365, 366, 367, 369, 370, 371, 173, 374, 375, 376, 377, 378, 380, 381, 383, 396, 405, 406, 407, 409, 411, 416, 425, 426, 432, 445, 447, 452, 454, 458, 461, 464, 468, 471, 473, 476, 477, 492, 503, 507, 508, 512, 513, 517, 530, 541.
In addition to these editions, the Library has at least 26 editions of Darwin's works not listed in Freeman.
Subject card catalogs
For a great many years, the Library has maintained subject card catalogs on Darwinism. These catalogs list any published work among the Library's holdings which mentions or discusses Darwin and/or Darwinism. They provide an unparalleled source for study of the influence of Darwin upon society and upon Western thought. There is one card catalog for books, containing approximately 2,800 entries, and another for journal articles, containing approximately 1,000 entries.
An effort has been made to make this appendix as complete as possible, but as the Library is constantly adding to its Darwin holdings, the careful scholar is warned that this compendium will be out of date in a short time.
Other Darwin Letters in the Greater Philadelphia Area
It is expected that this calendar will render unnecessary many visits to Philadelphia by Darwin scholars which would have been mandatory otherwise. While this is a beneficial result of the publication of this book, it is not without its harmful side effects. The worst of these would have been that the many miscellaneous Darwin materials in other institutions in the Philadelphia area might be neglected; this appendix is designed to prevent this by listing the results of a search by mail for other manuscript Darwin letters in select institutions in the greater Philadelphia area.
To conduct the search, a form letter was sent to the 31 institutions in the area judged by the editor to be the most likely to possess Darwin letters. Thirty institutions replied; they are listed below, and the name of the person responding is given for each institution.
Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia (Martha T. Pilling, Library Assistant)
Bryn Mawr College Library (James Tanis, Head Librarian)
Bucknell University (George M. Jenks, Librarian, Ellen Clarke Bertrand Library)
College of Physicians of Philadelphia (Ellen G. Gartrell, Assistant Curator, Historical)
Dickenson College (Danna Spitzform, Assistant to the Curator, Special Collections, Boyd Lee Spahr Library)
Drexel University (Michael Halperin, Archives and Special Collection)
Eleutherian Mills Historical Library (Betty-Bright P. Low, Research and Reference Librarian)
Franklin and Marshall College (Frances L. Hopkins, Reference Librarian, Fackenthal Library)
The Franklin Institute (Stephanie A. Morris, Associate Archivist)
Free Library of Philadelphia (Howell J. Heaney, Rare Book Librarian)
Hahnemann Medical College Library (Barbara Williams, Acting Librarian)
Haverford College Library (Edwin B. Bronner, Librarian)
Historical Society of Delaware (Gladys M. Coghlan)
Jefferson Medical College Library (Robert T. Lentz, Librarian)
Lafayette College (Ronald E. Robbins, Reference Librarian, David Bishop Skillman Library)
Lehigh University (James D. Mack, Director of University Libraries, Linderman Library)
Library Company of Philadelphia (Edwin Wolf, II, Librarian)
Pennsylvania State University (Dorrie Evans, Rare Books and Special Collections, Fred Lewis Pattee Library)
Philadelphia College of Pharmacy and Science Library (Elizabeth W. J. Chase, Librarian)
Princeton University Library (Mardel Pacheco, Assistant to Curator of Manuscripts)
Philip H. and A. S. W. Rosenbach Foundation Museum and Library (Clive E. Driver, Director)
Saint Joseph's College (Josephine Savaro, Head Librarian, Drexel Library)
Swarthmore College (Judith Pullam, Administrative Assistant, Thomas E. and Jeanette L. McCabe Library)
Temple University (Thomas M. Whitehead, Head, Special Collections Department, Samuel Paley Library)
University of Delaware Libraries (Stuart Dick, Special Collections, Hugh M. Morris Library)
University of Pennsylvania Libraries (Neda Westlake, Rare Book Collection)
Ursinus College (Calvin D. Yost, Jr., Librarian, Myrin Library)
Villanova University (Mary A. Dorrian, Readers Service, Falvey Memorial Library)
Wagner Free Institute of Science (Robert Chambers, Director)
and Widener College (Lee C. Brown, Librarian, Wolfgram Memorial Library)
The editor is grateful for the cooperation of these institutions and individuals.
Twenty-four letters of Charles Darwin were produced by the search. They are listed below, in chronological order.
1838 January 23 Sunday, to John Stevens Henslow; Al, S by init.; 4p.; courtesy of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
1843 July 19th, to Ernest Dieffenbach; ALS; 2p.; courtesy of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
1853 Jan. 10th, to Albany Hancock; ALS; 4p.; courtesy of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
?1854 Nov. 20th, to John Stevens Henslow; ALS; 2p.; courtesy of the Princeton University Library.
1860 March. 4th, to Joseph Leidy; ALS; 4p.; courtesy of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia (see their Collection 1). See calendar entry for this letter (number 202), page 69, above.
1860 May 8., to the Secretary of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia (see their Collection 330).
1862 April 25th, to Heinrich Georg Bronn; ALS; 6p.; courtesy of Lehigh University.
1871 July 1, to?; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
1872 Oct. 10th, to Alpheus Hyatt; ALS; 4p.; courtesy of the Princeton University Library (see the Hyatt and Mayer Correspondence).
1873 Feb 19, to William M. Canby; LS; 3p.; William M. Canby Correspondence, Society of Natural History of Delaware Archives, on deposit at the Historical Society of Delaware.
1873 May 7, to William M. Canby; LS; 2p.; William M. Canby Correspondence, Society of Natural History of Delaware Archives, on deposit at the Historical Society of Delaware.
1874 May 11, to Thomas Lauder Brunton; LS; 4p.; courtesy of the Princeton University Library.
1874 June 30., to?; LS; 2p.; courtesy of the College of Physicians of Philadelphia.
1875 Oct. 30th, to Messrs. Smith & Elder; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of Lehigh University.
1876 Aug. 21st, to Messrs. Smith & Elder; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of Lehigh University.
1876 Nov. 20th, to?; LS; 2p.; original in private possession of Dr. Seymour Adelman, c/o James Tanis, Head Librarian, Bryn Mawr College Library.
1877 March 7., to Messrs. Smith & Elder; LS; 4p.; courtesy of Lehigh University.
1877 June 6th, to?; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of Haverford College Library (Charles Roberts Autograph Letters Collection).
1880 Nov. 5, to?; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania.
1882 Feb 22, to?; LS; 4p.; courtesy of Princeton University Library (privately owned; from the private library of William H. Scheide, Princeton, New Jersey; no connection with Princeton University Library).
n.y. April 6th., to?; ALS; 3p.; courtesy of Lehigh University.
n.y. May 7, to?; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of Philip Schwartz, M.D., Medical Research Director, Warren State Hospital, Warren, Pennsylvania (privately owned by Dr. Schwartz).
n.y. Oct 2d., to?; ALS; 1p.; courtesy of Lehigh University.
n.y. Oct 14th, to "Madam"; ALS; 2p.; courtesy of Lehigh University.
All letters are listed with the permission of their owners, for which permission the editor is grateful.
Bibliography
Burkhardt, Frederick, The Correspondence of Charles Darwin (Cambridge: Cambridge Univ., 1985-). Currently 12 vols. See The Darwin Correspondence Project ( http://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/Departments/Darwin/pubns.html).
Other Finding Aids note
Many of these letters are described briefly in P. Thomas Carroll, An Annotated Calendar of the Letters of Charles Darwin in the Library of the American Philosophical Society (Wilmington, Del.: Scholarly Resources, 1976). Call no.: 012 D25c.
A comprehensive calendar of Darwin manuscripts is provided in Frederick Burkhardt and Sydney Smith, A Calendar of the Correspondence of Charles Darwin, 1821-1882 (N.Y.: Garland, 1985). Call no.: 016.091 D25b
Naval History Note
The Darwin Papers contain at least one item which may be of interest to naval historians:
Darwin, Charles. Letter to Lieutenant Charles Wilkes. 1836 October - 1836 November. Wishes to converse concerning Wilkes' "long...voyage." 1 page. (B D25.192).
African American History Note
One of the most important natural historians in nineteenth-century Britain, Charles Darwin provided the first compelling mechanism to account for organismal evolutionary change. In at least two letters in the Darwin collection, the naturalist reflects upon the nature of race. In a letter dated 8 October [1845], Darwin questions whether there is a connection between race and susceptibility to different types of lice. In a letter dated 25 October [1859], Darwin dispels other scientists' claims that there are several species of man.
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Bowerbank, James Scott, 1797-1877; Buckland, William, 1784-1856; Busk, George, 1807-1886; Eyton, Thomas Campbell, 1809-1880; Flower, William Henry, 1831-1899; Forbes, David, 1828-1876; Foster, M., Sir, (Michael), 1836-1907; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888; Gray, John Edward, 1800-1875; Gulick, John Thomas, 1832-1923; Günther, Albert C. L. G., (Albert Carl Ludwig Gotthilf), 1830-1914; Hancock, Albany, 1806-1873; Henslow, J. S. (John Stevens), 1796-1861; Herbert, John Maurice, 1808-1882; Hooker, Joseph Dalton, Sir, 1817-1911; Horner, Leonard, 1785-1864; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895; Lankester, E. Ray, Sir, (Edwin Ray), 1847-1929; Leidy, Joseph, 1823-1891; Lubbock, J. W., (John William), 1803-1865; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Milne-Edwards, H., (Henri), 1800-1885; Murchison, Roderick Impey, Sir, 1792-1871; Ogle, William, 1827-1912; Oliver, Daniel, 1830-1916; Owen, Richard, 1804-1892; Phillips, John, 1800-1874; Quatrefages de Bréau, Jean Louis Armand de, 1810-1892; Ramsay, A. C., (Andrew Crombie), 1814-1891; Romanes, George John, 1848-1894; Sclater, Philip Lutley, 1829-1913; Thwaites, George Henry Kendrick, 1811-1882; Wallace, Alfred Russel, 1823-1913; Walsh, Benjamin Dann, 1808-1869; Wyman, Jeffries, 1864-; Adaptation (Biology); Beyond Early America; Biology, genetics, eugenics; Coral reefs and islands; Evolution (Biology); Evolution--Religious aspects; Genetics; Geology--Great Britain--19th century; Heredity; Natural history--Great Britain--19th century; Natural selection; Naturalists--England; Race, race relations, racism; Religion and science--1860-1899; Transmutation of animals; Variation (Biology)
- Calendar of Letters
  - To [John Maurice] HERBERT; [Osmaston, near Derby], [1828 Sept. 13] Saturday Evening [pmk. Se 14/ 1828]; 1; ALS; 9x7.5 4p., add. [(S?) Herbert Esqr/ Post Office/ Barmouth/ N. Wales]
    Scope and Contents note
    Printed, with minor changes: Life and Letters, 172-73. p. 173, line 23, change "Yates" to "Yate". At end of letter is: "How is Buz & Bossy [sic]. am afraid you yourself must be grown terribly bumptious: Direct to Shrewsbury: if there is any thing you want I can send it for you to Barmouth. Such as gloves &c &c &c".
    General note
    1. Printed letter has erroneous date of Sept. 14, which was a Sunday.
  - To G [i.e. John Maurice] HERBERT; [pmk. Shrewsbury], [1828 October 3] Friday [pmk. Oc 4/ 1828; wmk. 1824]; 2; ALS; 9 x7.25 4p., add. [G. Herbert Esqr./ Court Calmore/ Welch Pool]
    Obliged for "labours in the science [of entomology]"; saw [?Thomas] Butler who told of Herbert in Wales; Herbert's courage cooled since CD left Barmouth; chiding letter from [Charles Thomas] Whitley, answered humbly by CD, received mere "acknowledgement of my extreme candour" and another charge of idleness; supposes Herbert enjoys Montgomeryshire and delights "all the little dear female hearts"; CD enjoys successful Music Meeting in Derbyshire, also good shooting, "Entomological pursuits", and the "Miss Foxes 1 are very pleasant girls"; Herbert can give CD beetles & butterflies, which Butler says Herbert has, when Herbert is in Shrewsbury; CD "shall go up [?to Cambridge] early," but not by 10th; Butler goes next Tues.; P.S.: Find more beetles; get lady with "strong imagination" to procure beetle with "face so very dreadful"; forgets Herbert's Christian name, christens him "G" [see above].
    1. The Misses Fox were the sisters of William Darwin Fox, CD's second cousin; the Music Meeting was held at the Fox residence. See "Darwin's Journal," 6.
  - To Cha[rle]s WHITLEY; 17 Spring Gardens, London, [1831 September 9] Friday Evening [pmk. 10 SE 1831; wmk. 1830]; 3; ALS; 9 x7.5 4p., add. [Chas. Whitley Esqr./ Post Office/ Barmouth/ N. Wales], end.
    Printed in facsimile: A Letter of Charles Darwin about Preparations for the Voyage of the Beagle, 1831 (Philadelphia: Friends of the Library, American Philosophical Society, 1971).
  - To J[ohn] M[aurice] HERBERT; Botofogo Bay, Rio de Janero [ sic], 1832 June [pmk. (SE?) 30/ 1832; wmk. 1830]; 4; ALS; 11 x8 3/4; 4p., add. [J. M. Herbert Esqr./ Fellow of St. Johns Coll:/ Cambridge; (forwarded to) (W?) Maddy Esqr/ Moreton/ Near Hereford]